The school of architecture that I studied at some 30 years ago
مدرسة الهندسة التي درست فيها بضع 30 سنة خلت
happened to be across the street from the wonderful art gallery
كانت تقع قبالة الطريق المؤدي إلى معرض الفنون المذهل
designed by the great architect Louis Kahn.
الذي تم تصميمه من قبل المهندس العظيم (لويس كان).
I love the building, and I used to visit it quite often.
أحب ذلك المبنى وغالبًا ما كنت أزوره.
One day,
في يوم ما،
I saw the security guard run his hand across the concrete wall.
رأيت الحارس الأمني يمرر يده قبالة الجدار
And it was the way he did it,
وقد كانت الطريقة التي فعل بها ذلك
the expression on his face --
والتعبير المرسوم على وجهه --
something touched me.
أمر ما أثر بي.
I could see that the security guard was moved by the building
لقد استطعت أن أرى أن الحارس الأمني قد تأثر بهذا المبنى
and that architecture has that capacity
وأن تلك الهندسة لها تلك القدرة
to move you.
على تحريك المشاعر
I could see it, and I remember thinking,
لقد استطعت أن أرى ذلك، وأذكر أنه مر بخاطري فكرة
"Wow. How does architecture do that?"
"يا إلهي! كيف يمكن للهندسة المعمارية أن تفعل ذلك؟"
At school, I was learning to design,
في المدرسة، كنت أتعلم التصميم
but here -- here was a reaction of the heart.
ولكن هنا كان تفاعلاً من القلب.
And it touched me to the core.
وقد كان تأثيرها علي عميقا.
You know, you aspire for beauty,
كما تعلمون، أنت تسعى إلى الجمال
for sensuousness, for atmosphere, the emotional response.
إلى الإثارة، إلى الاحساس، إلى الإجابة العاطفية.
That's the realm of the ineffable
هذه هي مملكة اللاموصوف واللامقاس.
And that's what you live for:
وذاك هو ما تعيش من أجله:
a chance to try.
فرصة المحاولة.
So in 2003, there was an open call for designs
إذًا، في 2003، كان هناك دعوة مفتوحة للتصاميم
for the Bahá'í Temple for South America.
من أجل معبد البهائي لأمريكا الجنوبية.
This was the first temple in all of South America.
كان هذا أول معبد في كامل أمريكا الجنوبية.
It's a continental temple,
إنه معبد قارّي،
a hugely important milestone for the Bahá'í community,
معلم مهم جدًا للمجتمع البهائي.
because this would be the last of the continental temples
لأنه يمكن أن يكون آخر معبد قاري
and would open the door for national and local temples to be built
ويمكن أن يفتج الأبواب لبناء معابد وطنية ومحلية حول العالم.
And the brief was deceptively simple
والموجز كان بسيطًا بشكل مخادع،
and unique in the annals of religion:
وفريدًا في السجلات الدينية
a circular room, nine sides, nine entrances, nine paths,
غرفة دائرية، تسعة جوانب، تسع مداخل، تسع سبل
allowing you to come to the temple from all directions,
تسمح لك بالدخول إلى المعبد من كل الاتجاهات
nine symbolizing completeness,
تسع رموز للاكتمال
perfection.
للكمال.
No pulpit, no sermons,
لا منبر وعظ، ولا خطب دينية،
as there are no clergy in the Bahá'í faith.
لأنه ليس هناك رجال دين في الدين البهائي.
And in a world which is putting up walls,
وفي عالم يضع جدرانًا،
the design needed to express in form
لا بد للتصميم أن يعبر في شكله على العكس،
It had to be open, welcoming
كان عليه أن يكون مفتوحًا، ومرحبًا
to people of all faiths, walks of life, backgrounds,
لكل الأشخاص من جميع الأديان، وأساليب الحياة والخلفيات
or no faith at all;
أو للذين بدون أي دين.
a new form of sacred space
شكل جديد من الأماكن المقدسة
with no pattern
من دون أي نمط،
or models to draw from.
أو مثال للاقتباس منه.
It was like designing one of the first churches for Christianity
لقد كان مثل تصميم أول الكنائس للديانة المسيحية،
or one of the first mosques for Islam.
أو أول الجوامع للإسلام.
So we live in a secular world.
إذًا، نحن نعيش في عالم علماني
How do you design sacred space today?
فكيف يمكن أن تصمم مكانًا مقدسًا اليوم؟
And how do you even define what's sacred today?
وكيف يمكنك أن تعرف ماهو المقدس اليوم؟
I stumbled across this beautiful quote from the Bahá'í writings,
لقد عثرت على هذا المقطع الجميل من الكتب البهائية
and it speaks to prayer.
وهي تتكلم إلى الصلاة.
It says that if you reach out in prayer,
إنها تقول أنك إذا ما وصلت في دعائك
that the pillars of your heart will become ashine.
فإن أعمدة قلبك سوف تنير.
And I loved this idea of the inner and the outer,
وقد أحببت تلك الفكرة عن الداخلي والخارجي
like when you see someone and you say, "That person is radiant."
كما عندما ترى شخصًا وتقول له: "ذلك الشخص منير."
And I was thinking, "My gosh, how could we make something
و كنت أفكر، "يا إلهي، كيف يمكننا أن نجعل من ذلك
architectural out of that,
عملاً معماريًا؟
where you create a building
حيث تبني مبنى
and it becomes alive with light?
ويصبح حيًا بالنور؟
Like alabaster, if you kiss it with light, it becomes alive.
مثل المرمر، عندما يلمسه الضوء يصبح حيًا.
And I drew this sketch,
لقد رسمت هذا الرسم،
something with two layers, translucent
شيء ما بطبقتين، شفاف،
with structure in between capturing light.
مع بنية تلتقط الضوء من خلالها.
Maybe a pure form, a single form of emanation
ربما شكل نقي، مجرد شكل للانبثاق
that you could imagine
قد تستطيع تخيله
would be all dome
يمكن أن يكون كله قبة.
and everything we kept making was looking too much like an egg.
وكل ما كنا نصنعه يشبه إلى حد كبير شكل بيضة
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
A blob.
بقعة.
So you search.
فتقوم بالبحث.
You all know this crazy search, letting the process take you,
كلكم تعرفون كيف هذا البحث المضني
and you live for the surprises.
ويجعلك تعيش للمفاجئات.
And I remember quite by accident
وأذكر أنني بمحض الصدفة
I saw this little video of a plant moving in light,
شاهدت مقطع الفيديو القصير هذا لنبتة تتحرك في الضوء
and it made me think of movement,
وجعلني أفكر في الحركية،
reach,
والوصول،
this idea that the temple could have reach,
كيف أن هذا المعبد استطاع أن يبلغ
like this reach for the divine.
مثل البلوغ إلى الآلهة.
You can imagine also
تستطيع أن تتخيل أيضًا
that movement within a circle could mean movement and stillness,
أن الحركية في شكل دائري قد تعني الحركة والسكون،
like the cosmos,
مثل الكون،
something you see in many places.
ما تراه في العديد من الأماكن
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
But rotation was not enough,
ولكن الدوران لا يكفي
because we needed a form.
لأننا نحتاج إلى شكل.
In the Bahá'í writings, it talks about
في الكتابات البهائية، هناك حديث عن المعابد
the temples being as perfect as is humanly possible,
التي كانت مثالية، أو بالأحرى أفضل ما استطاع الإنسان أن يصنعه،
and we kept thinking, well, what is perfection?
ففكرنا، "حسنًا، ماهي المثالية؟''
And I remember I stumbled into this image of this Japanese basket
وأذكر أنني اصطدمت بهذه الصورة لسلة يابانية
and thinking our Western notions of perfection need to be challenged,
وفكرت في أن معاييرنا الغربية للمثالية تحتاج لأن يتم تحديها،
that this wonderful silhouette of this basket, this wonkiness,
بسبب هذه الصورة الضلية الرائعة لهذه السلة، هذا الاعوجاج،
and that it has the kind of dimple of what you might imagine a shoulder
وأنها تمتلك نوعا من الدمل قد يجعلك تتخيل كتفا،
or the cheekbone,
أو وجنة،
and that kind of organic form.
أو أي شيء ذو شكل عضوي.
And so we drew and made models,
وهكذا رسمنا وصنعنا هذه النماذج.
these lines that merge at the top,
وهذه الخطوط المندمجة في الأعلى،
soft lines,
خطوط رقيقة،
which became like drapery
التي أصبحت كالقماش
and translucent veils and folding,
أو كالأغطية الشفافة والطيات
and the idea of not only folding but torquing --
والفكرة ليست مجرد الطي بل اللّي.
you remember the plant and the way it was reaching.
تذكرون النبتة وكيف كانت تمتد
And this started to become an interesting form,
وهذا بدأ يتحول إلى شكل مثير للاهتمام
carving the base, making the entrances.
وهي تنحت القاعدة، وتصنع مداخل.
And then we ended up with this.
وفي الأخير تحصلنا على هذه النتيجة.
This is this temple with two layers,
هذا المعبد بطبقتين،
nine luminous veils,
تسعة أغطية مضيئة،
embodied light,
ضوء متجسم،
soft-flowing lines
وخطوط ناعمة منسابة
like luminescent drapery.
مثل أقمشة مضيئة.
180 submissions were received from 80 countries,
180 عرضا تم تلقيها من 80 دولة
and this was selected.
وهذا ما وقع عليه الاختيار.
So we went to the next stage of how to build it.
وهكذا انتقلنا إلى المرحلة التالية وهي كيفية البناء.
We had submitted alabaster.
لقد اتفقنا على وضع المرمر
But alabaster was too soft,
لكن المرمر كان لينًا جدًا،
and we were experimenting, many experiments with materials,
وقد أجرينا اختبارات، العديد منها ، بالمواد،
trying to think how we could have this kind of shimmer,
في محاولة منا لمعرفة كيف نتحصل على هذا النوع من اللمعان
and we ended up with borosilicate.
وانتهى بنا المطاف بالبروسيليكات.
And borosilicate glass, as you know, is very strong,
وزجاج البروسيليكات، كما تعلمون، قوي جدًا.
and if you break borosilicate rods just so and melt them
وإذا كسرت قضبانًا من البروسيليكات وقمت بإذابتها،
at just the right temperature,
في درجة الحرارة المناسبة،
we ended up with this new material,
لتحصلنا على هذه المادة الجديدة،
this new cast glass which took us about two years to make.
الزجاج المسبوك، الذي تطلب منا قرابة السنتين لصنعه.
And it had this quality that we loved,
وقد حمل هذه الخاصية التي أحببناها
this idea of the embodied light,
هذه الصورة للضوء المتجسد،
but on the inside, we wanted something with a soft light,
ولكن من الداخل أردنا شيئًا بضوء خفيف
like the inner lining of a jacket.
مثل التخطيط الداخلي للسترة.
On the outside you have protection, but on the inside you touch it.
من الخارج لك الحماية، و لكن من الداخل تلمسها.
So we found this tiny vein in a huge quarry in Portugal
فوجدنا هذا العرق الضئيل في منجم ضخم بالبرتغال
with this beautiful stone,
مع هذا الحجر الجميل،
which the owner had kept for seven generations in his family,
الذي احتفظ به صاحبه طيلة سبعة أجيال من عائلته
waiting for the right project, if you can believe it.
في انتظار المشروع المثالي، إن استطعت تصديق هذا.
Look at this material, it's beautiful.
انظر إلى هذه المادة، إنها جميلة،
And the way it lights up; it has that translucent quality.
والطريقة التي تشع بها، إن لها تلك الخاصية الشفافة
So here you see the structure.
إذًا، هنا ترون البنية.
It lets the light through.
إنها تسمح بمرور الضوء.
And looking down,
وبالنظر إلى الأسفل،
the nine wings are bound,
الأجنحة التسعة متماسكة
structurally but symbolically strong,
في هيكلها ولكنها قوية في رمزيتها
a great symbol of unity:
رمز عظيم للاتحاد.
pure geometry, a perfect circle,
هندسة بحتة، ودائرة مثالية.
30 meters in section and in plan,
30 مترًا من التجزيء ومن التخطيط
perfectly symmetrical,
متناسقة بطريقة مثالية،
like the idea of sacredness and geometry.
مثل فكرة القداسة والهندسة.
And here you see the building going up,
وهنا ترون المبنى يرتفع،
2,000 steel nodes,
2000 عقدة من المعدن،
9,000 pieces of steel,
9000 قطعة من المعدن،
7,800 stone pieces,
7800 قطعة من الحجر،
10,000 cast glass pieces, all individual shapes,
10000 قطعة من الزجاج المسبوك، كلها في أشكال فريدة.
the entire superstructure all described,
قد تم وصف كامل البنية الفوقية
engineered, fabricated with aerospace technology,
وتمت هندستها، وصنعها بتكنولوجيا الفضاء،
prefabricated machine to machine,
وقد تم صنعها مسبقا آلة لآلة آليًا.
a huge team effort, you can imagine,
عمل فريق هائل، يمكنكم أن تتصوروا،
of literally hundreds,
من المئات
and within three percent of our $30 million budget
وفي 3% من ميزانيتنا التي تقدر ب 30$ مليون
set in 2006.
سنة 2006.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Nine wings bound together
اتحدت تسعة أجنحة معًا
forming a nine-pointed star,
مكونة نجمة تساعية النقاط.
and the star shape moving in space,
وشكل النجمة يتحرك في الفضاء
tracking the sun.
وهو يرصد الشمس.
So here it is.
وها هو ذا.
Audience: Wow!
الجمهور: يا إلهي!
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Hopefully, a befitting response to that beautiful quote,
على أمل سماع جواب لائق لتلك العبارة الجميلة
"a prayer answered,"
''لقد اُستجيب الدعاء.''
open in all directions,
مفتوحة في كل الأرجاء،
capturing the blue light of dawn,
ملتقطة ضوء الشفق الأزرق،
tent-like white light of day,
ضوء النهار الأبيض مثل خيمة،
the gold light of the afternoon,
الضوء الذهبي لبعد الظهيرة،
and of course, at night, the reversal:
وبالطبع، في الليل، الانقلاب:
sensuous,
حسي،
catching the light in all kinds of mysterious ways.
ممسكة بالضوء بكل الأساليب الغامضة.
And the site: it's interesting; 14 years ago when we made the submission,
أما الموقع فهو مثير للاهتمام منذ 14 سنة عندما قمنا بالعرض،
we showed the temple set against the Andes.
أظهرنا المعبد قبالة الانديز.
We didn't have the Andes as our site,
لم نكن نملك سلسلة جبال الانديز كموقع نملكه.
but after nine years, that's exactly where we ended up,
ولكن بعد تسع سنوات، هناك تحديدًا انتهى بنا المطاف.
the lines of the temple set against nothing but pure nature,
خطوط المعبد لا توحي بشيء سوي بالطبيعة النقية.
and you turn around and you get nothing but the city below you,
وأنت تستدير وتنظر حولك فلا ترى شيئًا سوى المدينة تحتك.
and inside, a view in all directions,
ومن الداخل، منظر يطل على جميع الاتجاهات،
radiating gardens
حدائق مشعة،
from each of the alcoves,
من كل ناحية من التجاويف،
radiating paths.
وطرق منيرة.
Last October, the opening ceremonies --
في أكتوبر الماضي، كانت احتفاليات االتدشين
a beautiful, sacred event,
حدث جميل ومقدس.
5,000 people from 80 countries,
5000 شخص من 80 دولة،
a continuous river of visitors,
نهر متواصل من الزوار،
indigenous people from all over South America,
سكان أصليون من كل جنوب أميركا
some who had never left their villages.
بعض منهم لم يسبق وأن غادروا قراهم.
And of course, that this temple belongs to people,
وطبعًا هذا المعبد ينتمي إلى الناس،
the collective, of many cultures and walks of life,
مجموعة الحضارات وأساليب الحياة
many beliefs,
والعديد من المعتقدات،
and for me, what's most important is what it feels like on the inside;
بالنسبة لي، أهم شيء هو كيف يبدو من الداخل.
that it feel intimate,
إنه يبدو حميميًا،
sacred,
مقدسًا،
and that everyone is welcome.
وأن كل شخص مرحب به.
And if even a few who come
وحتى ولو كان القليل من الزائرين
have the same reaction as that security guard,
يملكون نفس ردة فعل ذلك الحارس الأمني،
then it truly would be their temple.
عندئذ سيكون حقًا معبدهم.
And I would love that.
و لكنت احببت ذلك.
Thank you.
شكرًا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)